The greatest romance of all time!
Gone with the Wind is a drama, war, romance film directed by Victor Fleming.
The spoiled daughter of a Georgia plantation owner conducts a tumultuous romance with a
cynical profiteer during the American Civil War and Reconstruction Era.
Scarlett O'Hara, played by Vivien Leigh.
Rhett Butler, played by Clark Gable.
Melanie Hamilton, played by Olivia de Havilland.
Ashley Wilkes, played by Leslie Howard.
Mammy, played by Hattie McDaniel.
Gerald O'Hara, played by Thomas Mitchell.
Gone with the Wind is a 1939 American epic historical romance film
adapted from the 1936 novel by Margaret Mitchell.
It was produced by David O.
Selznick of Selznick International Pictures and directed by Victor Fleming.
Set in the American South against the backdrop of the American Civil War and the Reconstruction era, the film tells the story of Scarlett O'Hara (Vivien Leigh), the strong-willed daughter of a Georgia plantation
owner, following her romantic pursuit of Ashley Wilkes (Leslie Howard), who is married to his cousin, Melanie Hamilton (Olivia de Havilland), and her subsequent marriage to Rhett Butler (Clark Gable).
The production was troubled.
The start of filming was delayed for two years until January 1939 because Selznick was
determined to secure Gable for the role of Rhett, and filming concluded in July.
The role of Scarlett was challenging to cast, and 1,400
unknown women were interviewed for the part.
Sidney Howard's original screenplay underwent many revisions by
several writers to reduce it to a suitable length.
The original director, George Cukor, was fired shortly after filming began and was replaced by Fleming,
who in turn was briefly replaced by Sam Wood while taking some time off due to exhaustion.
Post-production concluded in November 1939, just a month before its premiere.
Gone With the Wind received generally positive reviews
upon its release on December 15, 1939.
While the casting was widely praised, the long running time received criticism.
At the 12th Academy Awards, Gone with the Wind received ten Academy Awards (eight competitive, two honorary) from thirteen nominations, including wins for Best Picture, Best Director (Fleming), Best
Adapted Screenplay (posthumously awarded to Sidney Howard), Best Actress (Leigh), and Best Supporting Actress (Hattie McDaniel, becoming the first African American to win an Academy Award).
It set records for the total number of wins and nominations at the time.
Gone with the Wind was immensely popular when first released.
It became the highest-earning film made up to that point and
held the record for over a quarter of a century.
When adjusted for monetary inflation, it is still
the highest-grossing film in history.
It was re-released periodically throughout the 20th century
and became ingrained in popular culture.
Although the film has been criticized as historical negationism, glorifying slavery and the Lost Cause of the Confederacy myth,
it has been credited with triggering changes in the way in which African Americans were depicted cinematically.
Gone with the Wind is regarded as one of the greatest films of all time, and in 1989, became one of the
twenty-five inaugural films selected for preservation in the United States National Film Registry.
The film explores themes of civil war, based on novel or
book, marriage crisis, loss of loved one, widow.
The tone is emotional.